सर, मैं कुछ बताना चाहता हूं.
हां बताइए
क्या हुआ?
सर, जब मैं अंग्रेजी बोलता हूँ तो लोग मुझ पर हंसते हैं।
वे मुस्कुराते हैं और एक दूसरे से बातें करते हैं।
मुझे बहुत बुरा लगता है।
मुझे लगता है कि मैं अच्छा नहीं बोल रहा हूं।
मेरी अंग्रेजी बहुत कमजोर है.
ओह मैं समझा।
आपको दुख होता है क्योंकि जब आप अंग्रेजी बोलते हैं तो लोग आप पर हंसते हैं।
लेकिन घबरावो नहीं।
गलती करना सामान्य बात है।
नई भाषा सीखते समय हर कोई गलती करता है।
आप सीख रहे हैं और सीखने में समय लगता है।
लेकिन सर, वे बहुत तेजी से बोलते हैं।
मुझे उनकी बातें समझ नहीं आतीं।
जब मैं बात करने की कोशिश करता हूं तो मेरे शब्द गलत हो जाते हैं.
मेरे दोस्त हँसते हैं और मुझे घबराहट महसूस होती है।
ठीक है।
आप अकेले नहीं हैं।
कई छात्रों को आपके जैसा ही महसूस होता है।
आपको बस अधिक अभ्यास और आत्मविश्वास की आवश्यकता है।
आइए साथ मिलकर अभ्यास करें।
चलिए सरल अंग्रेजी में बात करते हैं, ठीक है?
ठीक है सर.
आज हम सरल वर्तमान काल का प्रयोग करेंगे।
हम दैनिक जीवन, आदतें, और दिनचर्या के बारे में बात करने के लिए सरल वर्तमान काल का प्रयोग करते हैं।
उदाहरण के लिए, मैं कहता हूँ कि मैं छह बजे उठता हूं.
इसका मतलब है कि मैं इसे हर दिन करता हूं।
आप कह सकते हैं कि मैं सात बजे उठता हूं।
आओ कोशिश करे।
मैं सात बजे उठता हूं।
बहुत अच्छे।
इसे फिर धीरे से कहो।
I wake up at seven o'clock.
उत्तम।
देखिये आप अच्छा बोलते हैं।
अब आइए कुछ और वाक्य जोड़ते हैं।
जागने के बाद आप क्या करते हैं?
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
अच्छा।
कहो, मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।।
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
अच्छा।
अब दो वाक्यों को एक साथ बोलें।
मैं सात बजे उठता हूं.
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
बहुत बढ़िया।
आप तेजी से सीख रहे हैं.
चलो आगे बात करते हैं।
दांत साफ करने के बाद आप क्या करते हैं?
मैं अपने चेहरे को धोता हुँ।
मैं स्नान करता हूँ।
बहुत अच्छे।
आप ये भी कह सकते हैं, मैं अपना चेहरा धोता हूं और स्नान करता हूं।
इसे अजमाएं।
मैं अपना चेहरा धोता हूं और स्नान करता हूं।
बहुत अच्छा।
याद रखें, हमेशा धीरे और स्पष्ट रूप से बोलें।
डरो नहीं।
आइए और सिखे।
नहाने के बाद आप क्या करते हैं?
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
Yes.
I eat breakfast.
तुम्हारा नाश्ता में क्या खाते हो?
मैं अंडे और ब्रेड खाता हूँ।
कभी-कभी मैं दूध पीता हूँ।
उत्तम।
आप सरल वर्तमान काल का प्रयोग सही ढंग से कर रहे हैं।
मैं अंडे और ब्रेड खाता हूँ।
मैं दूध पीता हूँ।
बहुत अच्छा है।
धन्यवाद सर।
अब, नाश्ते के बाद आप क्या करते हैं?
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
अच्छा।
आप कह सकते हैं, मैं आठ बजे स्कूल जाता हूँ।
मैं आठ बजे स्कूल जाता हूँ।
बहुत अच्छा।
और आप स्कूल में क्या करते हैं?
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
मैं लिखता हूं।
मैं पढ़ता हूं
मैं अपने दोस्तों से बात करता हूँ।
बहुत बढ़िया।
आप बहुत अच्छा बोल रहे हैं।
चलिए एक छोटा सा पैराग्राफ बनाते हैं।
पहले मेरी बात सुनो।
फिर मेरे बाद दोहराओ।
मैं सात बजे जगता हूं।
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
मैं अपना चेहरा धोता हूँ और स्नान करता हूँ।
मैं नाश्ता करता हूं।
मैं आठ बजे स्कूल जाता हूँ।
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
मैं अपने दोस्तों से बात करता हूँ।
मैं सात बजे जगता हूं।
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
मैं अपना चेहरा धोता हूँ और स्नान करता हूँ।
मैं नाश्ता करता हूं।
मैं आठ बजे स्कूल जाता हूँ।
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
मैं अपने दोस्तों से बात करता हूँ।
बहुत अच्छे।
आपने सभी वाक्य स्पष्ट रूप से बोले।
देखो
आप अंग्रेजी बोल सकते हैं
आपको बस अधिक अभ्यास करने की आवश्यकता है।
लेकिन सर, कभी-कभी मैं शब्द भूल जाता हूँ।
ठीक है।
आप सरल शब्दों का प्रयोग कर सकते हैं।
अगर आप शब्द भूल जाते हैं तो रुकें नहीं।
कोई दूसरा आसान शब्द इस्तेमाल करें।
धीरे बोलो।
लक्ष्य संवाद स्थापित करना है, परिपूर्ण होना नहीं।
जी सर।
मैं समझता हूँ
आइए प्रतिदिन अधिक सक्रियता का अभ्यास करें।
आप दोपहर को क्या करते हैं?
मैं घर आता हूं।
मैं दोपहर का खाना खाता हूं।
बहुत अच्छे।
आप कह सकते हैं, मैं एक बजे घर आता हूँ।
मैं अपने परिवार के साथ दोपहर का भोजन करता हूँ।
मैं एक बजे घर आता हूँ।
बहुत बढ़िया।
दोपहर के भोजन के बाद आप क्या करते हैं?
मैं आराम करता हूं।
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
उत्तम।
आप यह भी कह सकते हैं, मैं आराम करता हूँ।
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
फिर से कोशिश करो।
मैं आराम करता हूँ।
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
बहुत अच्छा।
चलिए शाम के बारे में बात करते हैं।
तो फिर आप क्या करते हो?
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
मैं अपनी माँ की मदद करता हूँ।
महान वाक्य.
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
मैं अपनी माँ की मदद करता हूँ।
आप हर बार सरल वर्तमान काल का सही प्रयोग कर रहे हैं।
शुक्रिया सर।
अब मुझे खुशी हो रही है।
अच्छी बात है।
आपमें सुधार हो रहा है।
याद रखें, प्रतिदिन अभ्यास करें।
घर पर, अकेले में भी, अंग्रेजी बोलें।
आईने में देख कर बात करो।
आप कह सकते हैं, मैं जाग जाता हूँ।
मेँ खाता हूँ।
मैं काम पर जाता हूँ।
अभ्यास से आत्मविश्वास बढ़ता है।
सर, कभी-कभी मेरा बोलने का मन करता है, लेकिन मेरा दिमाग काम करना बंद कर देता है।
क्या बोलना है मैं भूल जाता हूं।
ऐसा सबके साथ होता है।
आप पहले अपने वाक्य लिख सकते हैं।
फिर उसे ज़ोर से पढ़ सकते हैं।
पढ़ते समय अपनी आवाज़ को सुनें।
हर दिन उन्हीं वाक्यों को दोहराने का प्रयास करें।
धीरे-धीरे, आपको बिना पढ़े ही याद आ जाएगा।
मैं कोशिश करूँगा।
अच्छा।
साथ ही, सरल अंग्रेजी के वीडियो भी देखें।
सुनो और दोहराओ।
लोगों के हंसने से मत डरो।
वे भले ही हंसें, लेकिन आप कुछ अच्छा सीख रहे हैं।
एक दिन वे हंसना बंद कर देंगे और आपकी बात सुनने लगेंगे।
धन्यवाद सर।
आपके शब्दों से मुझे शक्ति मिलती है।
यह मेरा काम है।
मुझे आप पर गर्व है।
You are brave to speak.
Now, let's say all your daily routine
again.
सुबह से रात तक।
ठीक है सर।
I wake up at 7 o'clock.
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
मैं अपना चेहरा धोता हूं और स्नान करता हूं।
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
मैं आठ बजे स्कूल जाता हूँ।
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
मैं अपने दोस्तों से बात करता हूँ।
मैं 1 बजे घर आता हूँ।
मैं अपने परिवार के साथ दोपहर का भोजन करता हूँ।
मैं आराम करता हूँ।
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
मैं अपनी माँ की मदद करता हूँ।
बहुत बढ़िया।
और आप रात में क्या करते हैं?
मैं रात का भोजन करता हूं।
मैं किताब पढ़ता हूं।
मैं रात 10 बजे सोता हूँ।
बहुत बढ़िया!
यह आपकी पूरी दैनिक दिनचर्या है।
आपने लगभग बिल्कुल सही बोला है।
अब, अगर आप इसका रोजाना अभ्यास करते रहेंगे, तो आपकी अंग्रेजी मजबूत हो जाएगी।
मैं अभ्यास करूंगा, सर।
मैं अब और नहीं डरूंगा।
यह हुई न बात।
बस याद रखें, अंग्रेजी में निपुण होना जरूरी नहीं है।
यह संचार के लिए है।
धीरे बोलो।
सरल शब्दों का प्रयोग करें.
और इसे हर दिन दोहराएं।
मुझे सरल तरीके से सिखाने के लिए धन्यवाद, सर।
आपका स्वागत है।
आपका आत्मविश्वास देखकर मुझे खुशी हुई।
मुस्कुराते रहो.
बोलते रहो.
और सीखते रहो.
जी हां, सर।
मुझे अब अंग्रेजी पसंद है।
इस तरह समझाने पर यह आसान लगता है।
यह तो बहुत ही अच्छी बात है।
याद रखो, तुम यह कर सकते हो।
अंग्रेजी खुशी से और बिना किसी डर के बोलें।
आप हर मिनट अभ्यास करके बेहतर हो रहे हैं।
जी सर।
मैं प्रतिदिन अंग्रेजी बोलूंगा।
अच्छा।
अब चलिए एक बार फिर साथ में अभ्यास करते हैं।
मेरे साथ बोलिए, मैं हर दिन अंग्रेजी बोलता हूँ।
मैं प्रतिदिन अभ्यास करता हूँ।
मैं प्रतिदिन सीखता हूँ।
मैं प्रतिदिन अंग्रेजी बोलता हूँ।
मैं प्रतिदिन अभ्यास करता हूँ।
मैं प्रतिदिन सीखता हूँ।
बहुत बढ़िया।
इसी तरह इंसान सीखता और आगे बढ़ता है।
हर सुबह जब आप सोकर उठें, तो इस वाक्य को दोहराते रहें।
मैं ऐसा ज़रूर करूँगा।
मैं प्रतिदिन अंग्रेजी बोलता हूँ।
उत्तम।
आप बहुत अच्छा कर रहे हैं।
सर, आज मुझे थोड़ा बेहतर लग रहा है।
कल मैंने दर्पण के सामने बोलने का अभ्यास किया।
लेकिन फिर भी, जब मैं अपने दोस्तों के साथ अंग्रेजी बोलता हूँ, तो मुझसे बहुत सी गलतियाँ होती हैं।
वे अब हंसते नहीं हैं, लेकिन मुझे शर्म आती है।
यह एक अच्छी शुरुआत है।
आपने अभ्यास किया, और सीखने का यही सबसे अच्छा तरीका है।
गलतियाँ करना सीखने का ही एक हिस्सा है।
आपको इस बात पर गर्व होना चाहिए कि आपने कोशिश की।
बताइए, आपने कल क्या अभ्यास किया था?
मैंने अपनी दिनचर्या को बार-बार दोहराया।
मैंने कहा, मैं सात बजे उठता हूँ।
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
लेकिन कभी-कभी मैं क्रियाएँ भूल जाता हूँ।
कोई बात नहीं।
आप धीरे-धीरे क्रियाएं सीख रहे हैं।
आज हम सामान्य वर्तमान काल और क्रियाओं के बारे में और बात करेंगे।
सामान्य वर्तमान काल का मतलब है कि हम उन चीज़ों के बारे में बात करते हैं जो हम हर दिन करते हैं।
यह एक आदत की तरह है।
आप कहते हैं: मैं जाता हूँ, मैं खाता हूँ, मैं काम करता हूँ।
हम क्रिया के मूल रूप का प्रयोग करते हैं।
क्या तुम समझ रहे हो?
जी सर।
हम पहले रूप का उपयोग करते हैंना?
बहुत अच्छे।
हम I, you, we, और they के साथ क्रिया के पहले रूप का उपयोग करते हैं।
लेकिन जब हम he, she, या it का प्रयोग करते हैं, तो हम S या Es जोड़ते हैं।
उदाहरण के लिए, मैं कहता हूं, मैं स्कूल जाता हूं।
लेकिन हम कहते हैं: वह स्कूल जाती है।
ओह, हाँ!
मैं यह जानता हूँ।
लेकिन मैं 'S' जोड़ना भूल जाता हूँ।
कई सीखने वाले इसे भूल जाते हैं।
लेकिन चिंता मत करो।
आप रोज़ाना छोटे वाक्यों का अभ्यास करके इसे ठीक कर सकते हैं।
चलिए कोशिश करते हैं!
मेरे बाद बोलिए, मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
अच्छा।
अब, 'I' को 'she' में बदलिए।
वह नाश्ता करती है।
ध्यान से सुनिए।
आपको कहना चाहिए, वह नाश्ता करती है।
वह नाश्ता करती है।
उत्तम।
और एक।
मैं फुटबॉल खेलता हूं।
अब, 'it' को 'he' में बदलिए।
वह फुटबॉल खेलता है।
बहुत बढ़िया।
आप बिल्कुल सही समझ रहे हैं।
चलिए थोड़ा और अभ्यास करते हैं।
वे अंग्रेजी पढ़ते हैं।
अब, 'it' को 'she' में बदलिए।
वह अंग्रेजी पढ़ती है।
यह सही है।
देखिए, जब क्रिया Y पर समाप्त होती है, तो हम Y को I-E-S में बदल देते हैं।
जैसे study, studies बन जाता है।
जी सर।
जब आप समझाते हैं, तो यह आसान हो जाता है।
अच्छा।
आइए, 'I' और 'she' दोनों का उपयोग करते हुए कुछ दैनिक दिनचर्या का अभ्यास जारी रखें।
मैं एक वाक्य बोलूंगा, और आप दोनों versions दोहराएंगे।
मैं 7 बजे उठता हूँ।
वह 7 बजे उठती है।
बढ़िया।
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
वह अपने दाँत साफ करती है।
बहुत बढ़िया।
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
वह स्कूल जाती है।
बहुत बढ़िया!
You are speaking very clearly.
Thank you, sir.
the rules.
Yes.
repeating and listening.
actions.
school?
मैं अपनी माँ की मदद करता हूँ।
Sometimes I make tea.
बहुत अच्छे।
What about your father?
What does he do in the morning?
He reads the newspaper.
He drinks tea.
बहुत बढ़िया।
You are using does correctly.
we also use does for questions.
For example, does he read the newspaper?
And the answer is yes, he does.
Try saying it.
Does he read the newspaper?
Yes, he does.
Great job.
Now, let's make some more examples.
Does she go to school?
Yes, she does.
Does he play football?
No, he doesn't.
Very nice.
When we say no, we use doesn't.
That means does not.
जी सर।
I understand now.
उत्तम।
the simple present tense.
Listen first.
I get up at seven.
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
I take a shower.
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
I play with my friends.
I come home at one o'clock.
I eat lunch.
I rest.
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
I go to bed at ten o'clock.
Now you try.
I get up at seven.
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
I take a shower.
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
I play with my friends.
I come home at one o'clock.
I eat lunch.
I rest.
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
I go to bed at ten o'clock.
बहुत बढ़िया!
That was clear and correct.
You are improving fast.
I am happy.
Before I could not say so many sentences.
Now it is easy.
day.
The more you speak, the better you become.
practice with your routine.
What time do you get up?
I get up at seven o'clock.
What do you eat for breakfast?
I eat bread and eggs.
When do you go to school?
मैं आठ बजे स्कूल जाता हूँ।
When do you come home?
I come home at one o'clock.
What do you do in the evening?
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
मैं अपनी माँ की मदद करता हूँ।
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
बहुत अच्छे।
conversations.
to anyone.
जी सर।
too.
Exactly.
You can ask your friends.
What time do you get up?
What do you eat for breakfast?
And they can answer.
This is good practice.
I will try that.
अच्छा।
Now let's add a few new daily actions.
Say after me.
I walk to school.
I talk to my teacher.
मैं किताब पढ़ता हूं।
I write in my notebook.
I listen to music.
I play with my little brother.
बहुत अच्छे।
sentences.
They are about things we do every day.
जी सर।
I understand the simple present tense now.
That's great.
Remember one thing.
Practice makes you confident.
wake up.
Say I wake up.
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
I take a shower.
action.
I can say I eat breakfast when I eat.
Exactly.
with the action.
This is a powerful way to learn English.
I like that idea.
I will speak English while doing my work.
That's excellent.
short stories and repeat the sentences.
too.
Sir, sometimes I feel I speak slowly.
Is that okay?
Yes, it is okay.
Speaking slowly is good for learning.
You will become faster with time.
Focus on being clear, not fast.
जी सर।
I will do that.
अच्छा।
Keep using simple sentences.
You can say I walk.
I read.
I write.
I play.
I help.
These are strong and easy.
now.
जी सर।
confident.
That is true.
Confidence is more important than speed.
doing great.
Thank you, sir.
tense.
बहुत अच्छा है।
it becomes natural.
You don't need to think about grammar.
You will just speak it.
I will try my best.
I know you will.
practice.
English.
English with other people.
When I meet someone new, I feel shy.
I don't know what to say first.
That's a good question.
Many students feel the same.
present tense to say what we do,
what we like, and who we are.
Let's practice small conversations.
Okay, sir.
I want to learn that.
अच्छा।
hello.
How are you?
The other person can answer, I'm fine.
Thank you.
Let's try.
Hello.
How are you?
I'm fine.
Thank you.
And you?
I'm fine too.
उत्तम।
That's how we start a simple talk.
After that, you can ask, what do you do?
Or where do you live?
Try asking me.
What do you do?
I am a teacher.
I teach English.
What do you do?
I am a student.
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
बहुत बढ़िया।
correctly.
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
It tells what you do every day.
Now, let's add more questions.
You can ask, where do you live?
Where do you live?
I live in Lahore.
I live in Karachi.
Very nice.
You can also ask about hobbies.
You can say, what do you like to do?
Or, what do you do in your free time?
What do you like to do?
I like to read books.
What about you?
I like to listen to music.
Great.
present tense.
what you like.
जी सर।
I understand now.
It's easy when you show examples.
That's right.
these ideas.
I will start.
Hello.
How are you?
I'm fine.
Thank you.
How are you?
I'm fine too.
What do you do?
I am a student.
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
That's nice.
Where do you study?
I study at city school.
बहुत अच्छे।
What time do you go to school?
मैं आठ बजे स्कूल जाता हूँ।
And when do you come home?
I come home at one o'clock.
अच्छा।
What do you do after school?
I eat lunch.
मैं आराम करता हूँ।
Then I do my homework.
बहुत बढ़िया।
What do you like to do in the evening?
I like to watch TV and listen to music.
That's great.
day.
sentence.
Thank you, sir.
someone new.
Yes, you can.
patterns.
For example, I like.
I go.
I do.
I have.
Let's practice with those.
Okay, sir.
Say after me.
I like tea.
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
I have many friends.
अच्छा।
many sentences.
For example, I like apples.
I go to the park.
I do my work.
I have a brother.
जी सर।
I can make many now.
I like chocolate.
I go to the market.
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
I have a sister.
बहुत बढ़िया।
You are using them correctly.
That's how you build confidence.
and does.
we, they and does for he, she,
it.
play football?
Okay, sir.
Let me try.
Do you like music?
Yes, I do.
Does she go to school?
Yes, she does.
Do they play football?
No, they don't.
Do you read books?
Yes, I do.
बहुत अच्छे।
Now you are making questions.
That's how we have real conversations.
You can use these every day with friends.
questions.
That's normal.
becomes.
them.
continue.
जी सर।
I will try to talk more.
Great.
now.
sentences.
I have four people in my family.
My father works in an office.
My mother cooks food.
My brother studies in school.
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
बहुत बढ़िया।
Now, let's add some more details.
What time does your father go to work?
He goes to work at nine o'clock.
What time does he come home?
He comes home at six o'clock.
अच्छा।
What does your mother do in the afternoon?
She cooks lunch and cleans the house.
बहुत अच्छे।
correctly.
That's a big improvement.
Thank you, sir.
I remember your examples.
That's the key to learning.
Listen and repeat.
Repeat every day.
comfortable with English sounds.
Let's repeat a few more.
He works in an office.
She cooks dinner.
He reads books.
She watches TV.
बहुत अच्छे।
These are simple but useful sentences.
You can talk about anyone using these.
जी सर।.
or my teacher.
Exactly.
Now, let's talk about likes and dislikes.
This is also in simple, present tense.
You can say, I like apples.
I don't like bananas.
She likes tea.
He doesn't like milk.
Try some.
I like chocolate.
I don't like coffee.
She likes music.
He doesn't like noise.
Very nice.
You said everything correctly.
we don't add s to the verb.
For example, he doesn't like.
Not he doesn't likes.
जी सर।
I understand.
अच्छा।
Let's add a few small dialogues now.
I'll say something and you answer.
Do you like English?
Yes, I do.
What do you do every morning?
I wake up early.
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
Where do you go after breakfast?
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
What do you do in the evening?
I study English and listen to songs.
बहुत बढ़िया।
You are talking naturally now.
This is how conversations happen.
Simple, short, clear.
stopping.
That's great.
You should feel proud.
Every small step makes you better.
Keep using the simple present tense.
your habits, your family, and your likes.
जी सर।
I can feel I am learning.
You are.
think in English, and use small sentences.
10 sentences like, I wake up.
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
I study.
I come home.
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
That will make your English natural.
I will do that.
I will speak every day and not be shy.
बहुत अच्छा है।
confident.
Sir, I want to tell you something.
classmates, they laughed at me again.
I felt very bad.
I wanted to stop speaking.
I think my English is not good.
Oh, I understand how you feel.
It hurts when people laugh, doesn't it?
is bad.
It means you are trying and they are not.
be proud of.
But sir, when I talk, I forget words.
My mind goes blank.
I start one sentence and then stop.
Everyone looks at me.
I feel so small.
कोई बात नहीं।
Every learner feels that way.
sometimes.
You are learning a new language.
You must make mistakes.
Mistakes are not bad.
They are part of learning.
Without mistakes, we can't grow.
me.
Maybe I can never speak well.
No, don't say that.
You already speak.
understand you.
That means you can speak.
confidence.
people say.
Just think about what you want to say.
nervous.
My hands shake.
I forget everything.
That's normal too.
Many people feel nervous.
You can train your mind to stay calm.
slowly.
You don't have to speak fast.
Clear and slow English is better.
I try to speak fast like others.
Maybe that's my mistake.
Yes, you don't need to copy others.
Speak at your own speed.
Let's practice something now.
sentences.
You can say, I wake up.
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
Say it with me.
I wake up.
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
अच्छा।
Simple and clear.
That's beautiful English.
correctly in the simple present tense.
जी सर।
I can say these sentences easily.
actions.
becomes.
Now let's add a few more.
I come home.
I eat lunch.
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
मैं आराम करता हूँ।
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
I sleep.
I come home.
I eat lunch.
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
मैं आराम करता हूँ।
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
I sleep.
बहुत अच्छे।
You see, you can describe your full day.
day, you can answer easily.
जी सर।
I can say, I wake up early.
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
I study.
I come home.
I eat lunch.
मैं टीवी देखता हूं।
I sleep.
उत्तम।
English.
Thank you, sir.
I feel better.
That's the right way.
confidently.
Remember, English is not a race.
It's a skill.
You build it step by step.
with verbs.
Like he play or he plays.
I get confused.
That's a very common mistake.
Let's practice it.
about he, she, or it, we add S to the verb.
For example, he plays football.
She cooks food.
It rains in summer.
Okay.
He plays football.
She cooks food.
It rains in summer.
अच्छा।
Now make a few sentences yourself.
He reads a book.
She sings a song.
It shines in the sky.
बहुत बढ़िया।
You used S correctly.
we, or they, we don't add S.
For example, I play football.
We study English.
They eat lunch.
I see.
So I play, but he plays.
Exactly.
That's the rule.
Let's repeat it a few times together.
I play.
He plays.
I read.
She reads.
I cook.
She cooks.
I go.
He goes.
बहुत बढ़िया!
You are learning fast.
break it into small steps.
जी सर।
I feel more confident now.
That's great.
do and does.
like apples?
Okay.
Do you like music?
Yes, I do.
Does she like music?
Yes, she does.
बहुत अच्छे।
Let's try negative sentences, too.
I don't like coffee.
He doesn't like milk.
Great.
we don't add S to the verb.
So he doesn't like, not he doesn't like.
जी सर।
I will remember that.
अच्छा।
conversation.
I will ask.
You answer.
Do you get up early?
Yes, I do.
What time do you wake up?
I wake up at seven o'clock.
Do you eat breakfast?
Yes, I eat breakfast every day.
What do you eat?
I eat bread and eggs.
What do you do after breakfast?
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
बहुत बढ़िया।
life.
others.
I can ask and answer simple questions.
That's right.
and your daily routine.
For example, my mother cooks breakfast.
My father goes to work.
My sister studies.
sentences.
My mother cooks food.
My father drives a car.
My sister goes to school.
उत्तम।
You are improving.
Now, if someone laughs, just smile.
You know that you are learning.
but one day they will listen
will be clear and confident.
I hope so, sir.
I want to speak like you one day.
You will.
Just keep speaking every day.
Practice in front of a mirror.
Talk to yourself.
Say things like, I wake up.
I wash my face.
I go out.
I meet my friends.
Repeat and repeat.
I can do that.
I can practice in my room every morning.
That's a great idea.
day.
For example, write, I go to school.
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
I talk with my teacher.
Writing helps you remember.
जी सर।
I like writing, too.
बहुत बढ़िया!
Keep writing and reading aloud.
Listen to English songs or short stories.
Try to repeat them.
sounds.
I will do that, sir.
Thank you for helping me feel better.
You are very welcome.
being perfect.
even when others laugh.
Every time you speak, you improve.
victory.
I understand now, sir.
I will not stop speaking.
I will keep trying every day.
That's the spirit.
आप बहुत अच्छा कर रहे हैं।
with my friends.
little.
This time, I didn't feel too bad.
smiled.
But I want to speak better.
not laugh.
I am very proud of you.
laughed.
That's real courage.
Every time you speak, you become better.
today?
school.
day.
laughed.
कोई बात नहीं।
understand what learning
learning the right way.
well.
I wake up early.
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
मैं अंग्रेजी पढ़ता हुँ।
Those are perfect sentences.
When I speak like that, I feel calm.
I don't need big words.
clearly.
Exactly.
Simple English is powerful English.
short, clear sentences.
You can do the same.
day.
What time do you wake up?
I wake up at seven o'clock.
What do you do after you wake up?
मैं दांत ब्रश करता हूँ।
I wash my face.
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
बहुत बढ़िया।
What do you eat for breakfast?
I eat bread and eggs.
Sometimes I drink milk.
That's great.
Now tell me what you do after breakfast.
मैं स्कूल जाता हूँ।
I study.
I talk to my teacher.
I play with my friends.
बहुत अच्छे।
sentences.
You can even make them longer now.
'clock.
I study English in science.
I play with my friends during break time.
Try it.
मैं आठ बजे स्कूल जाता हूँ।
I study English in science.
I play with my friends during break time.
बहुत बढ़िया!
You see how fluent you sound now?
जी सर।
clearly.
That's right.
important than speaking fast.
afternoon too.
What do you do when you come home?
I eat lunch.
Then I take a rest.
मैं अपना होमवर्क करता हूं।
After that, I help my mother.
बहुत बढ़िया।
simple present tense.
Eat, take, do, help.
These are all action words.
They show what you do every day.
जी सर।
I understand now.
do every day.
Exactly.
like.
Let's practice that.
What do you like to do after school?
I like to listen to music.
I like to draw pictures.
I like to talk with my friends.
बहुत अच्छे।
And what don't you like to do?
I don't like to wash dishes.
I don't like to wake up very early.
I don't like to fight with my brother.
Great.
English.
I like.
I don't like.
It's easy and natural.
people using he and she.
Tell me about your father.
My father works in an office.
He drives a car.
He drinks tea in the morning.
बहुत अच्छे।
Tell me about your mother.
My mother cooks food.
She cleans the house.
She watches TV in the evening.
बहुत बढ़िया।
And your brother?
My brother goes to school.
He plays football.
He studies math.
उत्तम।
well.
we add S to the verb.
Works, drives, plays, studies.
जी सर।
I remember that rule now.
अच्छा।
Now let's make it more fun.
it's correct or not.
He play football.
It's wrong.
It should be he plays football.
बहुत बढ़िया।
She go to school.
Wrong.
She goes to school.
They like tea.
Wrong.
बहुत अच्छे।
You are becoming confident.
Thank you, sir.
myself.
That's the sign of progress.
use in daily life.
For example, what do you eat for lunch?
What time do you go to school?
Do you like reading books?
What do you eat for lunch?
I eat rice and vegetables.
What time do you go to school?
मैं आठ बजे स्कूल जाता हूँ।
Do you like reading books?
Yes, I do.
I like reading English stories.
but I find them difficult.
That's normal.
Start with short stories.
Read slowly.
When you find a new word, don't stop.
Try to understand from the sentence.
Then read aloud.
Reading aloud helps your speaking.
I can do that.
I will read one page every day.
That's a wonderful plan.
mind and then repeat them out loud.
For example, I wake up.
मैंनें नाश्ता करता हूँ।
your mouth remembers the sound.
जी सर।
When I repeat, it feels easier.
Exactly.
practice.
short podcasts.
Listen carefully.
Pause and repeat what they say.
but I don't understand all the words.
कोई बात नहीं।
words.
your ears get used to English sounds.
Slowly, you will start to understand more.
That's true.
feel happy.
That's a great feeling.
Celebrate small progress.
forward.
You are not competing with anyone.
You are learning for yourself.
जी सर।
people everywhere.
That's a wonderful goal.
English helps you connect with the world.
But remember, it's not about being
perfect.
It's about being brave.
When you speak, speak with confidence.
keep talking.
I will try, sir.
I want to be brave when I speak.
You already are brave.
You speak even when others laugh.
That shows strength.
becomes stronger.
to fluency.
I understand now.
I just need to keep going, not stop.
Yes, make English part of your daily life.
When you wake up, say good morning.
When you eat, say I eat breakfast.
When you sleep, say good night.
Talk in English to yourself every day.
I can do that easily.
things.
That's perfect.
learn their first language
sentences again and again.
You can do the same.
Thank you, sir.
You make English feel simple.
daily.
Don't wait for big lessons or big words.
Just speak what you know.
Smile, be confident and enjoy the process.
जी सर।
अब मुझे पहले से ज्यादा आत्मविश्वास महसूस हो रहा है।
लोग चाहे कुछ भी कहें, मैं हर दिन अंग्रेजी बोलूंगा।
यही सबसे अच्छा वादा है जो आप खुद से कर सकते हैं।